An Inventory to the Pardee Lowe papers, 1911-1995
Hoover Institution Archives
- American Commission for Relief in China organizing files, 1937-1938 and undated. (Box 129)
  - Williams, Faith M. and Carle C. Zimmerman, Studies of Family Living in the United States and Other Countries: An Analysis of Material and Method, Washington, D.C.: United States Department of Agriculture, Miscellaneous Publications No. 223, 1935 December (Box 129)
  - Sociological profiles and case studies typescript drafts, 1930s. (Box 129)
    Consists mainly of duplicates of typescript material by Lowe that appears in the Sociological profiles and case studies files,
    - Dung Bo Choy (D. C. B.) (Box 129)
    - L. W. C. (Box 129)
    - L. L. (Box 129)
    - C. L., Miss (Mrs. W. C. L.) (Box 129)
    - Children (Box 129)
    - Dr. Ng Poon Chew (Box 129)
    - Yip Hay (Box 129)
    - First generation (Box 129)
    - Second generation (Box 129)
    - Third generation (Box 129)
    - Americanization (Box 130)
    - Intermarriage (Box 130)
    - Income (Box 130)
    - Housing and living conditions (Box 130)
    - Food and clothing (Box 130)
    - Recreation and play (Box 130)
    - Charity and religion (Box 130)
    - Medicine and health (Box 130)
    - Economic Activity (Box 130)
    - Imported technique and skills (Box 130)
    - Non-Chinese consumption (Box 130)
    - Chinese consumption (Box 130)
    - Both races (Box 130)
    - American-born, economics (Box 130)
    - Economic org., C. of C. (Box 130)
    - Immigration and laws (Box 130)
    - Population (Box 130)
    - Chinatown. (Box 130)
      Includes typescript notes related to history of Portsmouth Square, San Francisco, and the difference between the Chinese community versus Chinatown. Also includes some notes on New York's Chinatown
    - Emigration (Box 130)
    - Travel and transport (Box 130)
    - Early reception (Box 130)
    - Antagonism (Box 130)
    - Persecution (Box 130)
    - Prejudice and exclusion (Box 130)
    - Indifference (Box 131)
    - Customs and ideals (Box 131)
    - Family and clan authority (Box 131)
    - Family property, social rights (Box 131)
    - Respects -- attitudes (Box 131)
    - Duties (Box 131)
    - District loyalties (Box 131)
    - Chinafication (Box 131)
    - Phrases (Box 131)
    - Kinship terms and names (Box 131)
    - Ancestor worship, rituals, religion (Box 131)
    - Chinese patriotism (Box 131)
    - China-Japanese war (Box 131)
    - Family (Box 131)
    - Birth and babyhood (Box 131)
    - Sex and prostitution (Box 131)
    - Marriage (Box 131)
    - Divorce (Box 131)
    - Death (Box 131)
    - Education (Box 131)
    - Public grammar schools (Box 131)
    - High schools (Box 131)
    - Colleges and universities (Box 131)
    - Language schools (Box 131)
    - Chinese newspapers. (Box 131)
      Holographic and typescript notes concerning newspapers published in San Francisco and New York, currently and historically
    - Organizations (Box 131)
    - Six Companies (Box 131)
    - Family organizations (Box 131)
    - District organizations (Box 131)
    - Tongs (Box 131)
    - Special economic organizations (Box 131)
    - Children's organizations (Box 131)
    - Youth organizations (Box 131)
    - Native-born organizations (Box 131)
    - Older generation's organizations (Box 131)
    - Religious organizations (Box 131)
    - Political organizations (Box 131)
    - Social and pathological conditions (Box 131)
- Calendar pages, 1959-1961 (Box 132)
  1964-1965
- USIS memos from Lowe, 1964 (Box 132)
- Business cards, 1964 (Box 132)
- Research notes, probably 1920s. (Box 133-134)
  Consists of reading notes on a preprinted index card system
- Business cards, 1960s (Box 133-134)
- Stanford University course study notes, holographic, on index cards, 1920s (Box 135)
- Case file cards, 1930s. (Box 135)
  Records names, addresses, and case status of individuals; likely related to SERA relief
- Research notes, probably 1920s. (Box 136)
- Business cards and contact lists, 1960s and perhaps earlier (Box 136)
- Chinese language studies printed flashcards, probably 1920s (Box 137)
- Tatung Co. teaching files, 1987-1990 (Box 138)
- Chew, Caroline, "Development of Chinese Family Life in America: As Observed in San Francisco 'Chinatown,'" typescript master's thesis, Mills College, Professor Mary Roberts Coolidge, 1926 (Box 139)
- Clippings, 1989 (Box 139)
- Subject files, 1976-1979 (Box 140)
- Investments and financial records (Box 140)
- Subject file material, 1990s (Box 141)
- Investments and financial records (Box 141)
- Harvard Business School course notes, ephemera and clippings, 1930-1932 (Box 142-143.)
- Subject file materials, 1989-1994 (Box 142-143.)
- Harvard Business School course notes, 1930-1931 (Box 144-145)
- Who's Who in the Republic of China, 1963-1964 (Box 144)
- Printed manuals for teaching Mandarin Chinese, National Taiwan Normal University, 1982 (Box 145)
- Subject file material, 1990s (Box 146-149.)
- Printed material about Taiwan, 1960s-1990s (Box 146-149.)
  including The Free China Journal, 1990s
- Taitung Co. teaching files, 1990s (Box 146-149.)
- Dissertation draft appendix A typescript, 1955 (Box 149)
- PhD dissertation draft, typescript, 1955 (Box 150)
  Includes preface, body text except for chapter "1947," and appendices A through D
- Includes PhD dissertation draft, typescript, 1955 (Box 151)
- Subject files (Box 151)
- Material related work on UNESCO, 1960s-1970s (Box 151)
- Professor Kerner Festschrift correspondence, 1957 (Box 152)
- "Soviet-Chinese Relations, 1918-1941," typescript draft chapter, undated (Box 152)
- Dissertation research files, 1950s. (Box 152)
- Typescript and holographic notes, probably 1950s (Box 152)
- "1945 December" (Box 152)
- "Yalta Papers" (Box 152)
- College papers by Lowe and others (Box 153)
- Speech by Lowe (Box 153)
- Subject files, 1950s-1970s (Box 153)
- "1945 March" dissertation research file (Box 153)
- Clippings, 1930s (Box 153)
- Dissertation research files (Box 154)
  - "1945 January," (Box 154)
  - "1945 August" (Box 154)
  - "1946 January" (Box 154)
- Subject files, 1976 (Box 154)
- Asian Studies conference materials, Asilomar, 1976 (Box 154)
- Phi Lamda fraternity printed material, 1950s-1970s (Box 154)
- Clippings and reports for subject files, 1970s (Box 154)
- UNESCO correspondence and reports, 1956-1970s (Box 155)
- Subject files material, 1977 (Box 155)
- "Special MBA Library" clippings (Box 155)
- UNESCO reports, 1960s-early 1970s (Box 156)
- Chinese Digest, 1930s (Box 156)
- The Asian Student Orientation Handbook, 1962 (Box 156)
- "A Directory of the Foreign Communities of Alameda County, a Community Chest Agency for Foreign Communities," International Institute of Alameda County, 1936 (Box 156)
- Harvard School of Business notes, 1931 (Box 157)
- Clippings, 1920s-1930s (Box 157)
- UNESCO reports, 1960s-early 1970s (Box 157)
- "Source Material on International Education and Cultural Activities for the 1960s," U.S. Department of State report, 1961 (Box 157)
- Subject files, 1981-1982 (Box 158)
- "Source Material on International Education and Cultural Activities for the 1960s," U.S. Department of State report, 1961 (Box 158)
- Subject files, 1981-1982 (Box 159-160.)
- Clippings, 1981 (Box 161)
- Subject files, 1981-1982 (Box 162)
- Subject file clippings, 1981 (Box 162)
- Chinese Digest (San Francisco), 1937 (Box 163)
- The Chinese Student, 1936 (Box 163)
- Chinese Moslems in Progress, 1957 (1376), The China Islamic Association, People's Republic of China (in English, Chinese, and Farsi or Persian) (Box 163)
- Subject file materials, 1980-1981 (Box 163)
- Subject file materials, 1970s-1980s (Box 164)
- Subject file materials, 1950s-1980s (Box 165)
- Subject file materials, 1970s-1980s (Box 166-167.)
- "China-U.S. Trade 1936-1940" includes typescript and holographic notes, 1939-1941 (Box 168)
- Subject files, 1950s-1970s (Box 168-169.)
- Financial investment files, 1960s-1980s (Box 168-169.)
- Financial investment files, 1960s-1980s (Box 170)
- Research and writing files, undated, likely 1980s. (Box 171)
  Includes holographic research notes, undated, some on 1989 calendar pages
- Bank of Canton and banking draft writings and clippings, undated and 1980s (Box 171)
- Tatung Tech Business School teaching files, including newsletter profile of Lowe, 1976-1978 and 1982 (Box 171)
- Notes related to the Environmental Protection Agency (EPA), 1988 (Box 171)
- Printed materials and clippings, 1980s (Box 171)
- Income tax files, 1980s (Box 172)
- Subject files, 1940-1970s (bulk 1950s-1970s) (Box 172-176)
  Includes USSR subject files, with PhD coursework notes, and Department of State printed materials
- Printed materials related to Slavic Studies organizations and conferences, 1970s (Box 172-176)
- Department of State Education Officer files, 1930s-1970s (bulk 1960s-1970s). (Box 177-178.)
  Includes correspondence, reports, holographic notes, travel visit itineraries, personnel and contacts lists, and UNESCO clippings, organized by country
- USIA administrative files, 1950s. (Box 178)
  Includes agency history and other training documents
- Department of State files, 1960s-1980s (bulk 1960s-1970s). (Box 179)
  Includes staff directories, agency guides, printed State Department reports, and other documents on UNESCO.
- Ledger of daily expenses in Shanghai, 1948 June-1949 April (Box 179)
- UNESCO printed materials (Box 180)
- Subject files, 1950s-1970s (bulk 1960s-1970s) (Box 180-181)
- USIA administrative files, 1957-1963 (box 182) (Box 182)
- UNESCO printed materials, 1960s-1970s (Box 182-184.)
- Clippings, 1971 (Box 182-184.)
- Investment newsletters, 1970-1971 (Box 184)
- Clippings and other subject file materials, 1970-1972 (Box 185-186.)
- Department of State Education Officer files, 1960s-1970s. (Box 187)
  Consists mainly of memos and reports, with some briefing material, correspondence, and holographic notes
- Department of State Education Officer files, 1960s-1970s (Box 188)
- Subject files, 1950s-1960s (Box 188)
- Clippings, 1972 (Box 188)
- Subject files, 1950s-1960s (Box 189)
- Writing files, 1920s-1930s (Box 190-191)
  - "Delving into The Good Earth: Confessions of a Chinatownian in Hollywood," 1935 November - December, typescript with some holographic edits on verso (Box 190-191)
  - A first-person account of the challenges faced by a young, Bay Area, college-educated Chinese American man and his white wife, typescript with holographic edits, undated (Box 190-191)
- Subject files, 1920s-1970s (bulk 1920s-1930s) (Box 190-191)
  Including related to interracial marriage
- Administrative files, correspondence, script extracts, and other material related to casting for The Good Earth in San Francisco (Box 190-191)
- Writings related to economics coursework at Stanford and subsequent positions, 1920s-1930s (Box 190-191)
- Writings by others, 1930s, undated. (Box 190-191)
  - Hou, Dr. T. P. [about the white female author of "My Chinese Marriage"] undated, typescript (Box 190-191)
  - "Living Conditions in Chinatown, Prepared by a Study Group in the School of Social Studies, 177 Post Street, San Francisco, 1939," dedicated to Miss Alice Griffith, with photos (Box 190-191)
  - Unidentified, draft of article on the agrarian crisis of Kwangtung Province, China, undated, typescript with holographic corrections (Box 190-191)
- IPR administrative files, undated, probably 1930s. (Box 190-191)
  Includes typescript list of mailing addresses of National Councils of the Institute of Pacific Relations,
- Ephemera related to Bay Area Chinese Americans (Box 191)
- Cathay Chimes yearbook, probably 1930 (Box 191)
- Research files relating to San Francisco and San Francisco Chinatown, 1910s-1970s (bulk 1920s-1930s) (Box 192)
- San Francisco Juvenile Courts correspondence, draft writings, ephemera, and reports of data, 1930s (Box 192)
- "Personal History of a Chinese Doctor [Low D- C-]," draft writing, undated, probably 1930s. (Box 192)
  Includes information about the early newspaper publisher, Dr. Ng Poon Chew, his son Edward Chew, and their method for purchasing their home in Oakland during the period of whites-only housing covenants.
- Research files, 1920s-1960s (bulk 1940s-1950s) (Box 193)
  - Immigration (Box 193)
  - U.S. laws regarding people of Chinese descent (Box 193)
- Subject files (Box 193)
  - Language and language learning (Box 193)
  - Invention of automatic Chinese typesetting machines in 1963 by RCA and others (Box 193)
- USIS files related to work regarding information about development of Chinese typesetting machines. (Box 193)
  See also: box 276, materials on development of Sinotype
- State Department files, 1950s-1970s (Box 194)
- Cultural attaché in Taipei, 1950s-1960s. (Box 194)
  Includes correspondence, clippings, and other documents related to housing
- Subject files related to development of Taiwan (Box 194)
- PhD coursework, correspondence and draft writing on UNESCO work, 1950s-1970s (Box 194)
- UNESCO administrative documents, 1960s-1970s (Box 195)
  - Personnel files, 1960s-1970s (Box 195)
  - Biographical profile typescript, 1971 (Box 195)
- Research files (Box 195)
  - "Report of the American Economic Mission to the Far East," typescript, probably 1935 (Box 195)
  - U.S.-China trade article material, 1930s-1940, undated (Box 195)
- Clippings related to Taiwan, 1980s (Box 195)
- Chinatown research and writing files, 1920s-1930s (Box 196)
  - Letter to Dick [Richard LaPiere] in which Lowe characterizes the district organizations, family associations, and Consolidated Benevolent Society (formerly Six Companies), and all newspapers published in Chinatown, 1938 May 8. (Box 196)
    See also box 318-319
  - Data cards on Chinese American students at University of California, Berkeley, udated, probably 1930s (Box 196)
  - Correspondence and ephemera related to Chinese and Chinese-American students, 1920s-1930s (Box 196)
    Including advocacy on behalf of students being detained at U.S. immigration in 1924
- Taiwan subject files, mainly related to government and Kuomintang leaders, U.S. diplomatic lists, and lists of high-ranking Chinese government officials, 1960s (Box 196)
- Ephemera includes Chinatown business trade cards and New Year's cards, undated, some before 1906 (Box 197)
- China House, Berkeley, California files, 1950s (Box 197)
- Chinatown research and writing files, 1930s-1970s. (Box 197-198.)
  Draft writings and holographic notes, correspondence, photos, and printed material, largely relating to Chinatowns, especially San Francisco and Oakland, and Chinese American families
- "Dr. Way Chin Lowe's Personal History,", undated (Box 197-198.)
  Probably by Pardee Lowe
- Draft chapter, undated (Box 198)
- Chinatown subject files, 1950s and 1980s (bulk 1980s) (Box 199)
- SERA relief work regarding San Francisco Chinese and Chinese American population, 1930s (Box 199)
- Report typescript by Lowe, 1934 (Box 199)
- Chinatown and Chinese American research files, 1920s-1970s (bulk 1930s-1960s) (Box 200-203.)
- Federal Emergency Relief Administration and Community Chest of San Francisco relief efforts, 1930s (Box 200-203.)
- Lowe's freelance writing, personal and professional correspondence, holographic notes, and clippings from English and Chinese-language U.S. newspapers, all arranged to support further writing by Lowe on Chinatowns and Chinese Americans (Box 200-203.)
- American Committee in San Francisco for China Relief, correspondence, clippings, and expense reports, 1930s (Box 200-203.)
- Rice Bowl fundraiser newspaper clipping publicity photo of Lowe's father, Lowe Fat Yuen, San Francisco Chronicle, 1938 June 17 (Box 200)
- Chinese Digest issues, 1930s (Box 200)
- Correspondence with the American Red Cross on planning relief for war-torn China, 1930s (Box 201)
- Documents related to the forming of the American Committee for the Relief of China (ACRC), including typescript history, 1930s (Box 201)
- Golden Gate International Exposition, San Francisco, 1939 (Box 202)
- The World's Fair, 1930s-1960s (bulk 1930s) (Box 202)
- Taiwan research files (Box 203)
- Taiwan research files, 1960s-1970s and undated. (Box 204-205.)
  Includes draft writings by Lowe, undated, notes, correspondence, clippings and ephemera, writings by others, and UNESCO documents
- Subject files, 1930s-1970s. (Box 206-208.)
  Includes correspondence, unpublished reports, and clippings, largely related to Japan and Vietnam
- Subject files, 1950s-1960s. (Box 209-211.)
  Consists mainly of clippings and printed material about technical industries and natural resources, with some UNESCO reports and information on investing, particularly in securities
- Harvard Business School notes and typescript report, 1930s (Box 210)
- State Department bulletins, 1970s (Box 211)
- Clippings, 1971-1972 (Box 212-217.)
- State Department bulletins on countries, 1970s (Box 212)
- Correspondence and reports related to UNESCO, 1960s-1970s (Box 214-217.)
- Department of State Education Officer files, a typescript draft of memo from Lowe regarding his workload related to UNESCO, and recent trends in UNESCO budget and staff numbers, 1970 October 13 (Box 216)
- Printed material related to Lowe's work on UNESCO, 1960s-1970s (Box 218-220)
- Printed material on Chinese universities, in English and in Chinese (Box 219-220.)
- Printed material on Chinese culture, in Chinese (Box 219-220.)
- State Department files, 1950s-1970s. (Box 221-222.)
  Includes biographical materials, and supervisors' review
- Materials related to application to Foreign Service, with detailed information on Lowe's activities to date, 1955 (Box 221-222.)
- Travel to Asia for USIA and UNESCO correspondence, itineraries, other administrative documents, and ephemera, 1960s (Box 221-222.)
- Travel to Africa for work on UNESCO, 1970 (Box 221-222.)
  Including holographic letters and postcards to his wife and daughter
- USIA Television Service assignment, Japanese television crew filming in the U.S., itineraries, correspondence, expense reports, and clippings, 1965 (Box 221-222.)
- Subject file materials, mainly clippings, 1977-1978 (bulk 1978) (Box 223-224.)
- Subject file materials, 1970s-1980s (Box 225)
- Subject file materials, 1984-1985 (bulk 1985) (Box 226)
- UNESCO reports, position papers, and memos, 1960s-1970s (Box 227)
- UNESCO printed material, 1960s-1970s (Box 227)
- UNESCO printed materials and clippings, in English and in Chinese, 1970s-1980s (Box 228)
- "Taiwan Problem in International Relations," PhD student paper, 1950 (Box 228)
- Clippings, in English and in Chinese, 1976 (Box 229)
- Ephemera, in Chinese (Box 229)
- Printed materials, State Department bulletins and UNESCO report and clippings, 1975-1976 (Box 230)
- UNESCO, 1959-1970s (Box 231-232.)
- Association of Asian Studies conference report, 1959 (Box 231-232.)
- 4th Annual Sino-American Conference on Mainland China, presenters' papers, with notes, 1974 December 12-15 (Box 231-232.)
- History of the Institute of Pacific Relations from its founding in 1925 and the IPR's role in shaping U.S. public opinion on the Republic of China and the People's Republic of China, with discussion of Owen Lattimore, draft, undated, probably 1974, typescript and holographic (Box 231-232.)
- Association for Asian Studies correspondence, 1959-1972 (Box 231-232.)
- Association for Asian Studies newsletters, 1959-1972 (Box 231-232.)
- Clippings, in English and in Chinese, 1975-1976 (Box 231-232.)
- "Prospects for Chinese and East Asian Studies in American Institutions of Higher Learning," report, 1974 (Box 232)
- Subject files related to securities investing, 1950s-1970s (bulk 1970s) (Box 233-235)
- Subject files, 1980s-1990s (Box 235-236)
- Department of State Education Officer files, 1960s-1970s (Box 237-239.)
- UNESCO correspondence, reports, and printed material, 1960s-1970s (Box 237-239.)
- Taiwan subject files (Box 237)
- Clippings (Box 239)
- Creative writing files, 1936-1970s and undated (Box 239)
  Includes correspondence, 1936-1940, and research files related to creative writing projects, with holographic notes, 1936-1970s
- Subject files related to investing, 1960s-1970s (Box 240-243.)
- Clippings and ephemera related to Bay Area Chinese Americans, 1974 (Box 240)
  Including holographic notes from watching the original broadcasts of Philip P. Choy's documentary series Gam Saan Haak, 1974 May
- UNESCO and Africa materials, 1960s-1970s (Box 243)
- Soviet Union materials, 1960s-1970s (Box 244)
- UNESCO files, mainly regarding Africa, 1960s-1970s (Box 244-245)
  Including 1968 Nairobi conference, Kenya
- UNESCO files, 1960s-1970s (Box 246)
- Slavic languages PhD examination notes, 1952 (Box 246)
  In English and Russian
- USSR subject files, 1930s-1970s (Box 247-249)
- "Strategy of International Communism," notes from Lowe's attendance at Foreign Services Institute, 1959 July 13-24 (Box 247)
- Draft writings on the history of Moscow and the USSR, undated (Box 247)
- PhD history coursework materials, 1949-1952 (Box 247)
- Subject files on Hong Kong, 1950s-1970s (Box 249)
- Subject files, arranged by country or region, 1930s-1970s. (Box 250)
  Includes holographic and typescript materials and clippings related to Lowe's undergraduate studies in history,
- Department of State Education Officer files related to UNESCO, mainly concerning Asia, Afghanistan and Australia, 1950s-1970s. (Box 251)
  Consists mainly of holographic and typescript documents, reports, and some printed material
- "Hong Kong, the East-West Center and Stanford,", 1969 July 28. (Box 251)
  Debriefing after four weeks of travel to gather information on local conditions and UNESCO activity in eight Asian countries. Includes list of personnel present at debriefing and distribution list
- Asian Ministers of Education Conference files, Bangkok, 1965 November (Box 251)
- UNESCO and Asia files and typescript writing drafts, 1960s-1970s (Box 252)
- UNESCO and Asia files, 1960s-1970s. Materials on Asia, Asian Studies Associations, Cairo, and Middle Eastern countries (Box 253-254.)
- UNESCO and Africa files, 1960s-1970s (Box 255-258.)
- Israel files (Box 255-258.)
- Nairobi Conference materials, 1968 (Box 255-258.)
- Subject files on Chinese Communism, 1950s-1960s (Box 255-258.)
- Undergraduate coursework at Stanford, 1920s (Box 258)
- Subject files related to Communism, mainly in China ("Chicom") and the U.S.S.R., with some subject files on Taiwan, 1920s-1980s (bulk 1950-1970s) (Box 259-275.)
- Department of State Education Officer files related to UNESCO, and USIA work (Box 259-275.)
- Clippings (Box 259-275.)
- Typescript papers from graduate studies, likely arranged to support a writing project (Box 259-275.)
- USIA report detailing specific recommendations on counterintelligence strategies typescript, undated (Box 259)
- "Recent Chicom Policy on Latinization of the Chinese Written Language," USIA report, 1958 May 9 (Box 261)
  Regarding the standardization to pinyin Romanization for Chinese language transliteration
- Harvard MBA degree materials (Box 261)
- "Russia as an International Problem," Harvard Business School report, undated, probably 1930s (Box 262)
- UNESCO files, Southeast Asia, Pacific Islands, India, Iran, Pakistan, 1960s-1970s (Box 264)
- UNESCO files, Southeast Asia, Pacific Islands, India, Iran, Pakistan, 1960s-1970s (Box 266-268.)
- PhD studies, 1950s (Box 269)
- "Overseas Chinese," including files on Chinatowns, 1970s-1980 (Box 271-272.)
- Objectives and progress evaluation reports by Lowe, 1960s-1971 (Box 272)
- UNESCO files, Southeast Asia, Pacific Islands, India, Iran, Pakistan, 1960s-1970s (Box 273-274)
- Undergraduate degree at Stanford files (Box 275)
- UNESCO and State Department and USIA assignments files on "Overseas Chinese" and often including draft writings and arranged in subject files, 1920s-1970s. (Box 276-278.)
- Chinatowns and Chinese Americans writings and writing drafts, holographic and typescript (Box 276)